foreign
in
operations
it's a pleasure to have you here I'm
delighted to have you in Brazil the
Brazilian audience thank you very much
for having me
so John I think it's you're you have a
very
unique path in your life you were a CIA
agent you were very identified with the
institution by looking at your career
I'd say you were someone who assimilated
the values of that institution and they
enjoyed your job
I did and you did a 180 degrees change
in your life and I want to talk to you
about that I want to talk to you also
about what the CIA does in Latin
American we want I like to also touch
upon Bannon Stephen bannon's prison
and a little bit of the Brazilian
situation right now which we understand
America played a huge part in the recent
coup against Dilma Rousseff in the form
of an impeachment
so um John I want to start very simply I
want to know how can you can you tell us
how you became a CIA agent ah sure it's
a funny story funny strange uh and it's
not uh legal anymore and I'll explain
that but when I was in graduate school I
was at George Washington University in
Washington DC working on a master's
degree in legislative affairs and I was
taking a class called the psychology of
leadership and it was taught by a very
important uh psychiatrist
he was he had a PhD in political science
a PhD in Psychology and a medical degree
and he called himself a political
psychiatrist
very interesting class on how foreign
leaders make their decisions and so he
gave us an assignment to write a paper
one day where we had to follow our
bosses for a week and at the time I was
working for a trade Union in Washington
the United Food and Commercial Workers
Union and I had to follow my boss for
the week and then write a psychological
profile about him
well halfway through the week he and I
got into a very serious argument and I
called him a racist which he was
and he got very angry he balled up his
fists to punch me and I put my hands up
to protect myself and his face got red
and he said my penis is bigger than
yours
and I said what he said my penis is
bigger than yours
and I said you know what you're insane
and I quit and I walked out and I I
actually did quit
so I wrote my paper and I told this
story and I said that I believed he was
a sociopath with Psychopathic Tendencies
and I gave examples and I turned the
paper in
well a week later I got the paper back
and I got an A and in the margin the
professor wrote please see me after
class
so I went to see him he closed the door
of his office and he said to me look I'm
not really a professor here I'm a CIA
officer undercover as a professor here
and I'm looking for people who I think
would fit into the cia's culture I think
you would fit into the cia's culture do
you want to be a CIA officer
the truth was I was getting married in
six weeks I had no job I didn't know
what I was going to do so I said sure
I'd like to be a CI officer
and the next thing I knew after I passed
all of the tests I was in the CIA now
they can't do that anymore in 1993 we
passed a law called the um the Equal
Employment Opportunity Act and so it's
much less sexy you have to go to
www.cia.gov and click apply now but
that's how I got in it was it was
through that that private network of
contacts did he explain to you how you
would fit how he thought you would fit
in the CIA yes sir he did he did and he
recruited me into the analytics side of
the CIA and so for the first half of my
career I was the intelligence
community's classified biographer for
Saddam Hussein I was the one who
coordinated all of the psychological
profiles on Saddam Hussein and the
reason they gave me that job at such a
young age I was only
25 years old was because nothing ever
happened in Iraq it was the same
government since 1968 the same
leadership we had a very small Embassy
there we really didn't have any national
interests in Iraq until Iraq invaded
Kuwait and that act made me a star at
the CIA
[Music]
and
is it just do practice today that a CIA
professors or agents are on the cover as
a teachers in in institutions to
Recreation people no they don't they
don't do that anymore
um because of this Equal Employment
Opportunity Act but but what they did
they still have professors at
universities All Over America but it's
called The Scholar in Residence program
so now they come and say I'm a CIA
officer I'm going to retire in three
years so for my the final three years of
my career I'm going to be a professor
here so it's all very public and out in
the open they don't do it secretly
anymore
you told you became a star all of a
sudden can you can you elaborate on that
oh yeah it was the morning of August 2nd
1990. I had been at the CIA for about
nine months and I had just started to
feel like I really knew what I was doing
and I really knew what I was talking
about
and um
you know the night the night before
we all expected Saddam was going to
cross the border into Kuwait and he was
going to attack the the Kuwaiti uh uh
government and so I got up early and
sure enough during the night
Iraq had invaded Kuwait so I showered
and shaved and got dressed as quickly as
I could I got into the office at seven
o'clock and my boss said as soon as I
got there my boss said don't take your
jacket off we're going to the White
House
I had never been to the White House
before and again I'm only 25 years old
so we take a car to the White House and
the Marine escorts us into the Oval
Office
I've never been to the Oval Office and
so here I am
sitting with the president the vice
president the Secretary of State the
Secretary of Defense the National
Security adviser the director of the CIA
my boss and me
and so I remember thinking if my friends
could see this they wouldn't believe it
in a million years
and we're sitting there and the
President says well now what do we do
and everybody turns and looks at me
and I thought
this is my chance
so I said well Mr President Iraqi forces
entered the country at 2 A.M
they moved here they moved there this is
what happened the royal family fled to
Saudi Arabia I gave the full briefing
because I really did know what I was
talking about
and I had just coincidentally there was
there was a Kuwaiti uh physician who was
very political and was one of the
founding members of the popular front
for the liberation of Palestine and I
had written a paper about him the week
before just because he was interesting
to me and during the night the Iraqis
announced that he would be the new
president of occupied Kuwait so I was an
expert on this guy I knew everything
about him and uh
yeah I mean it it changed the course of
my career I became a star that day
you you held after that day you became a
star but your career didn't end there
you had a very senior position as a CIA
what exactly was your role as a senior
analyst and case officer what do you do
that the first seven years that I was an
analyst I I was promoted over and over
and over again uh working always on Iraq
and so just to give you an example I was
one of the co-authors of un Security
Council resolution 986 which created the
sanctions regime on Iraq it allowed Iraq
to purchase food and medicines but
pretty much nothing else uh I didn't
like that job you sit at a desk all day
you think the big thoughts and you write
papers that most of the time nobody
reads and every day for years and years
it was Iraq Iraq Iraq all the time
and I got bored
and so as you might imagine I spoke uh
fluent Arabic and fluent Greek and as it
turned out I was the only person in the
entire CIA that was fluent in those two
languages and then a job opened in
Athens in counter-terrorism operations
and they were looking for somebody who
spoke either Greek or Arabic so I went
to the officer in charge of hiring for
this job and I said look
um
I'm an analyst and I have literally zero
experience
in operations but I speak fluent Greek
and Arabic and he said are you kidding
me and I said no he said are you willing
to be tested I said of course
so they tested me and I tested fluent
and he told me the job is yours he said
it's easier cheaper and faster for us to
hire a linguist and teach him operations
than it would be to take an operations
officer and teach him how to speak Greek
and Arabic
so they gave me the job I went through
all of the operational training
weapons explosives driving recruiting
spies to steal secrets and they sent me
to Athens and I worked against
um one specific terrorist group called
revolutionary organization 17 November
and against a myriad of Arab groups uh
Abu nidal the libyans
pflp
pflpgc dflp they were all all in Athens
and so that's what I did for the next
two years
and as your spy you moved as you say you
moved several times abroad you flew in
an Arabic
you were almost assassinated by leftists
yes or as I know and you were part of
the operation that capture Abu Dubai
zubaida which is currently held in
Guantanamo yes and and you led a secret
life working for the CIA in the war on
terror
and but in December 2007 you decided to
blow the whistle and disclose this class
classified information officially
confirming that the US government was
using torture to interrogate Al-Qaeda
prisoners
and you were then the first office to
denounce in this practice and to say
goodbye to this goodbye to your entire
career yes so can you tell us about the
process that led you to such a 180
decision in your life yes
um I have always been a very firm
believer in the rule of law
and in respect for human rights and
civil rights and civil liberties that
made me unusual as a CIA officer
I I had been the chief of CIA
counterterrorism operations in Pakistan
after the 9 11 attacks and I was
responsible as you said for the capture
of Abu zubaida who was the you believed
at the time the number three in Al Qaeda
he was the first high-value Target that
we captured
and when I got home from Pakistan a
senior officer asked me if I was
interested in being trained in what he
called enhanced interrogation techniques
he explained to me what this was and I
said this sounds like a a torture
program
he said no it's not a torture program
the justice department approved it and
the president approved it and it's legal
I said this sounds bad I'm not
interested was it legal or he was just
telling you stories oh the the justice
department said that it was legal uh
there's a famous memo written by John
you and Jay Bybee to officials at the
justice department who essentially
turned the law on its head and and they
they claimed that it was legal but we
had a long a long history in the United
States with the 1946 torture act with
our signature on the uh United Nations
convention Against torture so to me it
was quite clear that this was an illegal
operation you didn't cross your mind
that maybe the CIA did this
well the CIA didn't do it until August
1st 2002. see in in 1975 the CIA caught
was caught
um overthrowing governments and
assassinating world leaders and the the
Congress created two oversight
committees the Senate select committee
on intelligence and the house permanent
select committee on intelligence and
from 1975 thanks to executive order
assassinations and covert actions to
overthrow governments were made illegal
well 911 changed everything the
president secretly revoked executive
order one two three
completely revoked it and so the CIA put
together teams that they were flying
around George Bush George W bush the CIA
put together teams that they flew around
the world to to murder you know whoever
they wanted to to murder
and they just decided that the torture
act didn't exist and I said if you're
going to torture prisoners I don't want
any part of it none whatsoever but I
waited for somebody to come out and say
something I thought certainly this is so
illegal it's so egregious that
somebody's going to come out and say
something and nobody said a word so from
early 2002 until December of 2007 nobody
said a word and then in December 2007 I
decided that I would say something and I
I had a request from ABC News one of the
major broadcast networks here in the
United States and I decided that I was
just going to tell the truth that I
thought the American people had a right
to know what the government was doing in
their name and they had a right to know
that the CIA was violating both U.S and
international law besides the fact that
torture just simply doesn't work and did
you know there was just uh how how you
were so certain because you need to be
so certain that this is actually
happening to go in the live TV in
American television to go and blow the
whistle you must have seen things
well have you yeah when I got home from
Pakistan I was promoted and I became the
executive assistant to the cia's deputy
director for operations and as the
deputy director's assistant I had access
to literally everything that the CIA was
doing around the world
and um they were reporting from Secret
prison sites all around the world what
they were doing to these prisoners and
there was just no question in my mind
that this was an illegal program
and how did you go can you I don't know
if you're able to say this but how did
you get all those documents that could
prove that you were not a crazy a former
CIA agent because you would be certainly
stigmatized coming from the CIA and
blowing the way so you would be the one
who's crazy and they will try to pin on
something else they certainly say this
guy is has any problems and he's trying
to make up things they will want to see
proof how do you get disproved
um I did not take out any documents from
the CIA that would be Espionage and so I
actually have a really great memory for
detail and so I was able to provide
detail of these illegal programs the
secret prison system uh-huh the the
international rendition program where
they would kidnap people and then take
them to other countries to be tortured
and uh and the torture program and I was
able to provide the journalists at ABC
news with the names of former CIA
officers who could confirm what it was
that I had said
psychologically what happens to you
after you went and blew the whistle
where were you expecting the entire
weight of the U.S government falls on
your head
what happened was within 25 24 rather
hours the CIA filed what's called a
crimes report against me with the FBI
saying that I had committed Espionage by
revealing the program
and so the FBI investigated me for a
full year from December of 2007 to
December of 2008 but then in December of
2008 they they closed the case and they
said that I hadn't violated the law
uh what I did not know was that three
weeks later when Barack Obama became
president uh John Brennan who was an old
colleague of mine and was named first
Deputy National Security advisor and
then CIA director
he asked the justice department to
secretly reopen the case against me and
I didn't know that for the next three
years the FBI was following me
everywhere they were tapping my phones
they were intercepting my emails and
then finally in January of 2012 I was
arrested and charged with five felonies
including three counts of Espionage in
in the United States as in most
countries Espionage is one of the
gravest crimes with which an American
can be charged National Security and in
many cases it carries with it the death
penalty and so um
yeah psychologically it's very hard
so when we receive that do you did you
have a lawyer do you I I hired a dream
team of the best defense lawyers in
Washington and and to tell you the truth
they came to me because this was such a
major case on not just a national
security issue but on constitutional
issues I have a constitutional right for
example to freedom of speech
and if a program is illegal
by by definition it can't be classified
you can't classify a crime for the
purpose of keeping it from the American
people you told you you told us in the
in the uh in the program that chasing
Justice that I had the pleasure to be to
share the panel with you you thought
about American laws that do not accept
that you classify documents as illegal
when you try to hide crimes which law is
that that would be interesting to
oh it's a lot that's been on the books
for a very long time since actually
since 1975 since the the revamping of
the of the CIA in fact George W Bush's
uh classification Czar was was his
unofficial title I guess he was the
chief classification officer at the
Pentagon
um has said in court that
as much as 80 percent of classified
documents uh in the U.S intelligence
Community should not be classified
they shouldn't have been classified in
the first place
that leads to my next question
so
um you are the first CIA officer to be
convicted for passing classified
information you served two years in to
the press in in federal prison it seems
that you're just telling me that it
would not be correct for them to hide
their crimes under the cloak of
confidentiality
so the US justice system seems to work
to corroborate the cia's illegal
practice and illegal version when they
indicted you yes yes and to it seems
accomplished of the U.S justice system
to hide torture as as a exactly right
about this yes in fact what tradition do
you think the CIA has in the U.S
judicial system and in the legislative
it's very very deep and I think that we
see examples of that every day in the
Julian Assange case in in my own case in
Discovery we received memos from the
justice department and these memos
included a series of three one was from
John Brennan at the CIA to Eric Holder
the attorney general and it said charge
him with espionage
and holder wrote back and said my people
don't think he committed espionage
and John Brennan wrote charge him anyway
and make him defend himself
and that's what they did and they waited
until I went bankrupt and then they
dropped all the Espionage charges
because they knew I hadn't committed
Espionage but this is what they do oh
yeah it was Revenge with the justice
system yes and and the justice
department does what the CIA tells it to
do it's been like that for many years oh
so can you explain a bit can you explore
a bit with us the doj Department of
Justice day connection with the CIA yeah
it's quite important for us to
understand sure the the specific
connection and and I'll apologize to
your viewers in advance because this is
a little bit bureaucratic
but there's a specific office at the
justice department called the office of
legal counsel olc
the purpose of olc is to decide if
things that the CIA wants to do are
legal or illegal
so let's say the CIA says we want to
overthrow the British government
olc will say oh you can't do that that's
not legal
so the CIA says okay we want to
overthrow the Libyan government okay
that's legal you can do that
but what happens is that olc becomes
really little more than a rubber stamp
so that if the CIA really really wants
to do something olc will justify it
legally so for example the CIA wanted to
create a torture program so they went to
olc and said we want to create a torture
program olc said well you can't do that
because torture is illegal we have the
federal torture Act of 1946 and we're
signatories not just signatories but we
were the the actual drafters of the
United Nations convention Against
torture and they said well at the CIA we
really really want to do this torture
program so just figure it out
so what they did in this series of memos
called the you baby memos
um was they said that well yes the law
says that you can't torture people but
what is torture really if it doesn't
leave a mark on your body is it really
torture we think it's not so
torture is legal
and
because this was all classified it was
all top secret nobody could sue them in
the federal courts and say wait a minute
the law is very clear torture is illegal
and this ubib memo is wrong nobody knew
there was a You by B memo because it was
classified
so that's how the CIA exerts its
influence now fast forward
to
Mike Pompeo Mike Pompeo in 2000 whenever
it was nine
not nine
2017 decides he wants to kill Julian
Assange
because of the Vault 7 Revelations he's
so angry he says let's kill him
they go to the office of legal counsel
and they say we want to kill this guy
well you can't because he's an
Australian National and you can't kill a
citizen of an Allied country especially
a five eyes Country Canada Australia New
Zealand us UK you can't do it
but olc said
well what we can do is we can say that
he's a representative of a hostile
non-state intelligence service
that would make it legal
well it wouldn't actually but they would
argue this was not just rhetoric or
dramatic license to qualify him this was
a technical term that he employed to
authorize so that nobody realized that
nobody realized that at the time in fact
we laughed about it I even wrote an
article about it like why is he saying
something so stupid that this is a
hostile non-state actor well there was
actually a very serious reason why he
said it because then it allowed olc to
legally justify the assassination of
Julian Assange so why was Julian not
assassinated because what happens is
it goes from the CIA to the office of
the legal counsel
and then from the office of the legal
counsel it goes to the general counsel
the attorneys at the National Security
Council at the White House well whatever
the CIA and olc want to do they just
approve it they never say no then it
goes to the National Security advisor if
he signs it it goes to the president and
the president signs it and be it becomes
something called a presidential finding
what happened in the case of Jillian
Assange is it got to the National
Security advisor H.R McMaster General
H.R McMaster and he said are you people
insane we're not going to murder an
Australian National
and he's the one who killed it
that's why
let's say Pakistani oh again he would be
dead he'd be dead today
what do you think is going to happen to
Julian Sarge if he's extradited what do
you see the perspective if Julian
Assange is extradited I think he'll die
in an American prison but I really don't
think that he will be extradited uh
certainly this is going to take some
time because there are several more
levels of appeal uh available to the
United States uh the latest appeal was
just heard in the court of appeals I
think Julian's going to win there
um if Julian wins the United States
could elect to uh to appeal to the
British Supreme Court and if they lose
there they could appeal again to the
European Court of Human Rights but there
are three precedents at the European
Court of Human Rights where where
European Nationals who the United States
was seeking to extradite one their case
is against extradition because of the
way that the United States uses solitary
confinement as a punishment
Nils melzer the UN special repertoire on
torture has said repeatedly over the
years that the U.S practice of solitary
confinement is a form of torture the
international standard is that you
cannot be held in solitary confinement
for more than 15 days
well in the United States we have
prisoners who have been in solitary
confinement for as long as 44 years I
know he'd just be one of them just being
released
yes now how in the world is that person
supposed to come out of prison with his
mind in order after not having human
contact of any kind for 44 years of of
course it's torture and so I'm confident
the Europeans are not going to force
Julian Assange to the United States
so help so help us God you've been
you've been imprisoned yourself in in
can you explain to us a bit this
experience
because you've been not only in prison
but you've been prison for doing the
right thing yeah you've been breathing
before it was a little tough saving
lives I think it's if you I think if you
kill someone you went to prison it must
be La it's not this heart but when you
do the right thing and you are
stigmatized and sitting there alone that
is another level can you and you told me
that you sympathize with Lula with
Mandela that you took strength from
those kind of people uh I just want to
hear a little bit about that
yeah let me make two comments about that
first of all
um yeah I went to a real prison I didn't
go to a country club where I could play
tennis and you know read books all day I
went to an actual prison with bad people
drug kingpins and Mafia Dons and fully
one-third of the prison population was
pedophiles so this was a tough place
um I decided that the CIA had trained me
to live in some of the worst places on
Earth
and God knows that I had served in
places that were far far worse than this
prison
and so I just decided to rely on my CIA
training to make sure that I stayed safe
and stayed at the top of the social Heap
were you afraid of your of your
existence of your physical existence
oh yeah in the beginning
but one of the things that the CIA
taught us to do in training was to make
strategic alliances
and so I took that very very seriously
the the Italians and when I say Italians
I mean the the members of the five
organized crime families uh in New York
uh adopted me for two reasons number one
because I'm Greek and the Italians and
the Greeks are very very close yeah and
number two
um I hate the FBI as much as they do I
see and so they pulled me into their
Circle very quickly
uh a rumor got started somehow that I
was an assassin for the CIA and the
Nazis loved that
and so
so I had no problem with the Nazis the
Aryans
um at the same time the week that I went
to prison uh Louis Farrakhan the the
leader of the Nation of Islam uh a black
Muslim group here in the United States
uh wrote a newspaper article in his own
newspaper uh saying that I was a hero of
the Muslim people because I gave up my
freedom in the name of Human Rights and
so the blacks were okay with me
and then the only ones that I was a
little more worried about were
um the Mexican cartel members oh really
yeah because they're violent just for
the sake of violence and and so
um one of them was in my cell he was one
of my cell mates and he asked me one day
if I was educated and I said yes and he
asked me if I would write his appeal
and I said well I'm not a lawyer and he
said yeah but you're educated
and I said you know what you're right
how hard could it be to write an appeal
I said sure I'll write your appeal I
didn't have anything else to do but but
sit in my cage all day long okay so I
did some research and I wrote his appeal
and um and he lost but uh but I didn't
charge him anything which surprised him
and I said no no I I have people on the
outside I I don't I don't need any money
what are you gonna give me ten dollars
worth of tuna fish you know or or or
Diet Coke or something it
you don't owe me anything so he spread
the word among the Mexicans that I was a
good guy and and so I never had any
problem with anybody so that was the
first thing the second thing was
that
I have great admiration for people like
Nelson Mandela and president Lula and uh
Martin Luther King and these these were
people who in my view were Gravely
wronged by their governments wronged in
far worse ways than I was
you know people who went to prison for
for decades people like Martin Luther
King who was assassinated because of
what he believed in and so if they could
forgive the people who wronged them
I could forgive the people who wronged
me
I only lost two years of my life not 35
years
and uh and so I just decided that the
future looked brighter than the past and
I was going to treat it as as water
under the bridge and so that's what I
did and and it shows it totally serious
thank you John you told me that you have
a Brazilian partner I do I do my
girlfriend is is a Brazilian uh National
we've been seeing each other for three
years she uh began as a journalist and
then uh finished a PhD in anthropology
so she worked as an anthropologist for
many years
studying uh the tribes of the Amazon
it's funny when we first started dating
she would disappear for six weeks eight
weeks at a time because she was so far
up the amazon that there was no cell
phone connectivity and she would come
back with wonderful pictures uh and then
she got a job uh with the inter-american
Development Bank uh helping to do
large-scale development in Brazil
Argentina Uruguay and Paraguay
um
because really the the issue that's most
important to her and her life is
fighting poverty and so that's what
she's dedicated herself to but yeah
we've had a fun time together three
years is kind of a long time and things
are going well great and I hope you can
come to Brazil soon and look forward I
hope to be there to receive you thank
you so much Jonah I have more questions
and this question is about a bit what's
going on in Brazil as you know as you
say Lula was Gravely wronged uh digma
Rousseff as well she was teached and but
the good thing is that you know Glenn
Greenwald received the throw of
information and they intercept licked
conversations which are Now official
court documents and they revealed that
the former judge and Minister former
Justice Minister narrow Sergio Moro and
he's prosecutor in the former prosecutor
darlingong they had a secretive extra
official and collusive collaboration
with the U.S Department of Justice
Joseph doj they just mentioned he has
insertion with the CIA and in this
anti-corruption everything under the
name of anti-corruption which was the
car wash operation the same operation
that led to Lula's imprisonment prevent
him to run the election in 2018
and what's opened the way for the
bolsonaro era so um The Intercept I'm
going to read it here revealed that they
secretly hosted a delegation I'm I'm
going to quote The Intercept quote they
secretly host delegations of the U.S
officials and coached and facilitate U.S
efforts to secure cooperation of
Witnesses in corruption investigation
into state-controlled oil giant
petrobrass with the approval of car wash
prosecutors the U.S negotiated deals
with some witnesses without following
any of the procedures on the treaties
which you would have given Brazil gave
the greater control over the process so
they went to the extra official way of
collaboration whatever that might have
been
so can you explain to us in general line
how the US what is the U.S government
role in such foreign operations in how
they Co-op these figures like tomorrow
and darlingo people in Brazil have a lot
of difficult to understand that this is
not conspiracy theory that is yeah oh no
what no this is this is not a conspiracy
theory this is this is a prime example
of the United States interfering in the
internal affairs of another country now
this is something that in any other
situation would result in a very strong
diplomatic protest right because it
really is interference
and it's not just the the justice
department
I would say I would warn people that
it's also the state department in fact I
would go so far as to say that it begins
with the state department it includes
the justice department it includes
certainly the treasury Department
because in many cases money laundering
charges just appear out of nowhere or
corruption charges that's the treasury
Department and now we we have to worry
about the Department of Homeland
Security as well and the whole time
you also have the CIA working behind the
scenes
so this is a this is not a conspiracy
this is a concerted effort by the most
important elements of the American
government
to essentially install leaders overseas
who they like and who are going to
support the American agenda
and to destroy not just to push out but
to destroy
those leaders who don't support the
American agenda also you and I were
talking uh offline a little before we
started filming and I said how in the
United States we have two parties we
have the Democrats and the Republicans
and the Republicans called the Democrats
the radical left and the Democrats call
the Republicans the radical right the
truth is they're both right-of-center
parties right the Democrats are a little
bit right of Center and the Republicans
are very right of Center there's nothing
radical about the Democrats there's
nothing left-wing about the Democrats
but with that said overseas anybody
whose ideology is to the left of the
Democrats is communist
and communism
is a threat to the United States that's
the mentality here here we are all these
years after the Berlin Wall fell and the
Soviet Union broke apart people are
still obsessed with the idea of
progressive political movements overseas
here in the United States people are up
in arms right now that Daniela Ortega
won the presidency of Nicaragua again
for example
the Biden Administration that's supposed
to be so Progressive and so radically
left-win refuses to re-establish
diplomatic relations with the government
of Cuba
well look at Brazil look at president
Lula look at Dilma Rousseff
they had no uh ill intent against the
United States right they were
democratically elected officials of
their country and the United States
decided now we don't like them we want
somebody far more right-wing so instead
of interfering in the election or maybe
I should say just interfering in the
election a a program was hatched to
destroy them
and so poor uh president Lula ended up
in prison uh president Rousseff ended up
with her with her uh reputation
destroyed
and uh the world ended up with jair
bolsonaro
I want to add few to this conversation
if you allow me to please you you talked
about the CIA and that's not a
conspiracy theory I mean those leaks
well those leaks showed for anyone who
has
ears and could read could see the leaks
and could say informed in their own
mouth and their own admission that they
have been involved extra officially with
investment of justice but not only that
there was more like messages where this
prosecutor darlingo referred to the Lulu
imprisonment as a gift from the CIA
playing and then
Sergio Moro the judge who put Lola in
jail they made an unprecedented visit to
the CIA headquarters yes Langley yes
he's coming to power with the backing of
Wall Streets according to the
investigations of Brazil wire so we know
knowing that the CIA operates the
Safeguard the U.S corporate and
political interests worldwide in light
of this fact what do you think could
have happened there to each extent of
the CIA had a role in the collaboration
of the Brazilian Car Wash operation how
do you think that operation could have
happened
oh very easily I think first of all let
me let me stress how unusual it is
for a foreign leader to go to CIA
headquarters very very unusual now every
once in a while I would be called on to
be a foreign leader
but it was usually like I did one time
the prime minister of uh Fiji
or the Deputy Prime Minister of Albania
or something like that but for
um the president of a major world
country like Brazil to go to CIA
headquarters is the judge and the judge
that I I when you first mentioned that I
was trying to think of another example
where something like that happened and I
couldn't think of any time while I was
at the CIA that anything like that ever
happened it's so inappropriate that I
can't even imagine how it was approved
in the first place unless it was part of
an operation to
essentially destroy Lula and take over
the Brazilian government I think that's
really what it what it came down to
you know there's a joke at the CIA it's
kind of an open joke
that intelligence is a cash business
right when I was in Pakistan I spent I
in six months I probably spent 10
million dollars in cash we were throwing
money out of the side of helicopters
right at Afghan Warlords and you know
money I couldn't spend the money fast
enough literally an unlimited budget
well you know what uh it's not the CIA
is not a verse to uh making a little
deal on the side maybe this judge
would like to have a new house or maybe
his son would like to go to an American
University all expenses paid well he
went to 60 Minutes nobody knew who he
was he wasn't 60 minutes
see
so there there's always a deal everybody
has a price
you know they teach us in spy school
uh what the motivating factors are uh
why why would people want to work for
the CIA why would they want to spy for
the CIA 90 for 90 of them it's money
right money is easy we have more money
than we can count we'll just give you as
much money as you want if you produce
for us for some people it's ideology
uh they're True Believers in the United
States and um they they want to do
something to help the United States that
there aren't many people like that it's
a couple of percent
but the other one is the other
motivating factor is hatred
um
you hate your boss
he passed you over for promotion you
hate the other political party you hate
Lula
you want to ruin him
you know hatred is a very motivating
factor it is money is secondary
but if you're someone who who has such
deep hatred for someone and you're in a
position to destroy his life you'd be
surprised at the number of people who
actually pursue that
and so I think we're seeing a
combination of things here I wouldn't be
at all surprised if money changed hands
probably a lot of money
but I also wouldn't be surprised if
hatred was one of the motivating factors
beautiful so it's not only instrumental
there is a and there is something that
happened lately while we were talking
about the Stephen Bannon prison right
here offline and we know that one of the
sounds joybo scenario has four Sons
who uh
obey at the same time they obey variable
scenario they also are the one
dominating jazz versus quite of a weird
relationship they have with each other
but one of his sons was accused of
helping plotting uh the capital Invasion
on the 6th of January he apparently was
involved with one of the groups
of that helped and he was actually there
on the sixth yeah he was with one of the
guys there was one of the head figures
that helped in the capital you and he
has a long story of being thinking that
he's American of American patriotism and
part of his theology is it's based on
that feeling
and she did Stephen Brown now has been
jailed
um do you think it's possible that the
CIA FBI might be monitoring the sound of
Jairo bolsonaro oh absolutely
absolutely there's still they're still
monitoring me and I'm nobody so uh yeah
you know
we we've got a situation here in the
United States where the technology now
is so Advanced that everybody literally
everybody is liable for surveillance the
the NSA has built a new facility in the
state of Utah that has enough computer
memory storage that it can save every
phone call every text message and every
email from Every American for the next
500 years
yes
um the the courts have also ruled
that warrantless wiretapping is not a
constitutional violation and so it's not
because you know all you have to say is
Terrorism yes 911 terrorism right and so
um so everybody is liable to being spied
on you know it's not just against the
law but it's a part of nsa's Charter
their founding Charter that they are not
allowed to spy on U.S persons that is an
American citizen or anybody in the
United States on an immigrant Visa but
they do that every day
and the courts refused to stop them so
take that and couple it with the idea
that the FBI's job is to surveil
everybody right it's a law enforcement
organization and the cia's job is to is
to at least electronically surveil
foreign Nationals you know we know for
example thanks to Ed Snowden that the
CIA was intercepting Angela merkel's
cell phone for years well she's one of
our closest friends
so that just confirms the idea that that
we spy on everybody
everybody do you think just a lot of a
scenario should be afraid of the CIA I
don't think he should be afraid because
I think the CIA loves him they love
strong men and fascist you know
right-wing politicians
um but I would also assume if I were
bolsonaro that
um all of his Communications are being
monitored all of them
and you know you might ask why uh you
would ask why tradition yeah it seems
like
yeah yeah but uh you know
The information collected isn't just for
to sit in in CIA files it's to share
with American companies to give them a
leg up on trade on banking on finance
you know you can use this this close
hold information in any number of ways
and and usually at the end of the day
the reason is a financial one
very interesting
I want to touch upon a bit a bit of a
different thematic
um I myself as a lawyer I consider that
one of the biggest threats of
brazilian's democracy those Christian
fanatic charts from the charismatic
charismatic movement originated in deep
south of the United States yes we call
here neopentecostal churches and they
introduced deliberately and a strategy
from Washington as a way to reduce the
influence of the left leaning Catholic
Movement Like The Liberation theology
that's right
and today they constitute a ascending
political power in Brazil they left
those small churches all the garages
um they have an incredible political
influence they predicate anti-democratic
ideas they spread hate speech defamation
of the progressive Force they deny
science they control really minds and
hearts in a very in a way that they
cannot be liable for and Gerald fought
from a U.S president admitted that the
CIA used missionaries as an agent
she is can you confirm this and is this
still practice
um I can confirm it and
um officially they stopped the practice
in 1975 during the Ford Administration
but that's just the CIA now the FBI uh
cultivates these these movements you're
exactly right about uh about these uh
these figures for example I was in
Guatemala not too long ago and one of
the things that I learned there are that
the two fastest growing religions in
Guatemala which of course is a
traditionally Catholic country uh the
two fastest growing religions are
Evangelical this right-wing Evangelical
Christianity and Saudi style Islam oh
really where does that come from one of
the biggest buildings in Guatemala City
is a brand new mosque that the Saudi
royal family has built and Guatemalans
are converting to Islam now
I'll tell you as a practicing Greek
Orthodox and and we're very very similar
of course to the Catholic Church going
back to the time of Christ
we don't even consider these groups to
be Christian
ity we consider them to be right-wing
political groups
and in many cases in most cases
um
their their biggest issue their biggest
cause is
um is the support of Israel they want
all Jews to return to Israel because
it'll hasten the return of Christ right
they want to to push the second coming
of Christ and the only way to do that is
to get all Jews back to Israel so that's
oftentimes what they focus on but you're
exactly right these right-wing groups
are very political far more political
than they are religious they're
dangerous uh and they um and they are
actively in opposition to what they
perceive to be
uh uh left-wing Liberation theology and
it's funny because in many cases the
theology is not Liberation at all it's
it's just mainstream Catholicism it is
it is it's original it's just the
Primitive christianism what we call it
that's it air and it it's to it's very
hunting what you you're telling me you
were telling me the CIA is supporting
such groups and through those groups
they will dominate people
right this is this is something that you
would affirm it's not for sure in theory
oh no you you put somebody on a salary
you give them a thousand two thousand
five thousand a month and uh you tell
them what to do and they report back to
you every month yeah and what about
Latin America
full CIA why CIA so we have a
long-standing history with CIA when you
were talking about the 75 this torture
lore before that CIA agents trained
Brazilian militaries for torture
um Brazil Uruguay Argentina Mexico even
all over the place why are they so
interested in Latin America why are we
the targets yes because this is our
backyard
right we have the Monroe Doctrine which
is still an overriding concern in
American foreign policy we see this as
our area
we don't want the Russians here we don't
want the Chinese here we don't want
anybody else I wrote an op-ed in 2000
eight for the Los Angeles Times uh
talking exactly about this and how um
the Iranians had invested in a bicycle
Factory in Venezuela and you would have
thought that they were building nuclear
weapons to point at the United States
the CIA was so so crazy angry that the
Iranians would open a bicycle Factory
uh we don't want anybody in Latin
America other than us
that's it
and you telling me that um so the CIA it
would be very interesting to understand
how the CIA may change its culture
whether you have a trump in power
whether you have a bad in power do you
see any changes just the business usual
intelligence policy and foreign policy
are almost always consistent now
certainly if the CIA it's consistent
across parties whether it's a Democrat
or Republican nothing is going to change
Donald Trump was an unusual pres
president president because he was just
so
out of the mainstream he was such a
right wing
protectionist extremist
that there were some differences in
foreign policy but Donald Trump is gone
and uh no matter who the Democratic and
Republican nominees are going to be in
2024 I don't think there will be any
significant changes in foreign policy
defense policy or intelligence policy
so Brazil Latin America seems we exist
as such countries we have been colonized
country in a way either by the
Portuguese or the Spanish or either by
the the American and North Americans
do you see a way out for us to be so for
our sovereignty I do how can we how can
we go against this huge machinery
that is in America
this was something that I learned in
Pakistan
um if you want the U.S out of your
business the only way to do it is to
educate your population and develop your
economy
that's really that's really it otherwise
you're going to have American meddling
and manipulation and you know the United
States is going to come down there with
these giant sacks of money uh bribing
your officials and essentially buying
your foreign policy the only way to to
get that to stop is is through education
and economic development
do would you do all over again
absolutely would you do all of her yeah
why was it worth it
it was worth it somebody had to say
something about the torture program
I I just assumed somebody else would but
I'm I'm glad I did the cost was high it
was very high but um but it was worth it
I can sleep at night my children are
proud of me and uh and it was worth it
it had to be done
great John I just like to hear your
final words from you and thank you for
this absolutely amazing interview it
will associate insights and I don't
think how many people has the
privilege to talk to ex-ci agent willing
to say anything you know like any of us
yeah I probably say Asia don't even say
they're a proper name so it's such a
huge privilege for all us here to this
interview thank you so much openers your
shiny personality and to know you it is
very very interesting life and this
Insight I don't think we got to see this
in a lot in another time maybe another
lifetime that's right I'll be so happy
to to hear your final words oh thank you
you know I we have to keep up the fight
just remember
I tell myself this all the time
we're the good guys we're right and
they're wrong and so if you believe in
in what you're committed to
um just keep fighting and keep pushing
because eventually uh everybody else
will come around you know a clear
majority of the American people
supported a torture policy but I knew
torture was wrong and now we've gotten
to a point where torture has been
outlawed in the United States
that Gina haspel the former head of the
CIA admitted that the torture program
was a mistake Senator John McCain stood
up on the floor of the Senate and said
that the American people would never
have known what their country was doing
if I hadn't told them so if you believe
what you believe
then stick with it and keep fighting
John actually I have two more questions
sure do you have time sure a little bit
more time so you sent me an article The
Kite Runner which I couldn't open
straight way from the your front page of
New York Times for saving the lives or
many children Afghanistan can you can
you tell us about this after I left the
CIA I was working for a private company
and I got a call from Paramount Studios
asking me if I would consider going to
Afghanistan to rescue some children
who had appeared in the film The Kite
Runner
apparently there were bootleg copies of
the film that had made their way to
Afghanistan from India
Afghans are very simple people
many of them and they couldn't tell that
this was just a made-up story they
thought that it was real and there were
two objectionable scenes in the movie
one where a boy was raped by another boy
and another where a boy was forced to do
a homoerotic dance for a member of the
Taliban
so
um the studio told me go to Afghanistan
assess the security situation assess the
danger to the children and then if the
children were indeed in danger to get
them and their families out of the
country so I took two weeks of vacation
I went to Afghanistan secretly I went
through India
and
met with a lot of people determined that
these children really were in danger
and to make a long story short I ended
up getting
27 people
the children and all of their family
members out of the country I bribed
everybody in the Ministry of Foreign
Affairs to give us exit visas and
passports
and then we rented Vans and drove to the
airport and I went and I said I need 27
seats plus one on the first flight out
of here and I don't care where it goes
and they they said well the first flight
because my my goal was to get everybody
to Dubai right okay I said we need to
get to Dubai well they said well there's
a flight to India in 11 hours and then
you can go from India to Dubai I said no
I we got to get out right now
and they said well
um there's a flight to Iran
well I'm I'm an American and a former
CIA officer I can't fly to Iran
but I had no choice so I said I said
give me 28 tickets to Iran so
so we flew to Iran on care the Iranian
it's an Iranian Airline
and uh we got off the plane in Iran and
I got 28 more tickets to Dubai I mean
there were flights like every two hours
to Dubai a friend of mine met us in
Dubai and um
we ended up enrolling the children in
schools in Dari language schools we got
jobs for the fathers and we got
apartments for all 27 of them you know
to live together as families
and uh
rescued them and then I flew back home
and went right back to work to do my
regular job when was that that was 2007
I was working at Deloitte in touch at
the time one of the big four accounting
firms and do you know what happened to
those children
yes I'm very disappointed to tell you
that after a year the parents decided to
go back to Afghanistan
and uh the studio asked me to call them
so I did and I said you're making a
terrible mistake
right a terrible mistake that you're
going to go back we we gave all of you a
brand new life in Dubai the emiratis
gave them uh residency visas there's no
reason to go back
uh but they did they all went back all
of them all 27 of them
and then I lost touch with them
would you so so now that we have the
withdrawal from Afghanistan and we know
the balance of this war
what do you think of the withdrawing
what do you think the Futures holds for
Afghanistan and the people I think we
should have withdrawn you know in
December of 2001. uh our our legislative
mandate in Afghanistan was to destroy Al
Qaeda and we destroyed Al Qaeda by
December of 2001. uh Al Qaeda for all
intents and purposes no longer exists
there are little tiny elements of it
spread around Yemen uh the Sahel but in
Afghanistan Al Qaeda doesn't exist
anymore
and so you know as soon as George W bush
said the words
nation building we knew we were in
trouble we knew we were in trouble sure
we wanted to capture or kill Bin Laden
uh but there was no Al Qaeda left to to
attack what do they want to do there why
do you think they stayed
I think they stayed for a couple of
reasons um I think one because of the
rare earth metals that uh that exist in
Afghanistan they're worth a trillion
dollars and now the Chinese are mining
them but I think also we wanted to just
kind of screw the Russians at the end of
the day that we wanted to prove to
ourselves and to the Russians that that
we could succeed where the Russians
failed and the truth is that
historically nobody has succeeded in
Afghanistan going back to Alexander the
Great
so you know another thing too and this
is something that Americans never
understood or at least they never
appreciated the Taliban didn't come you
know from the Moon and and land in
Afghanistan
the Taliban are the sons
of afghans
right every family in Afghanistan at
least every every Sunni Muslim family in
Afghanistan has members of the Taliban
in their family these are not foreign
Invaders they're not space aliens
they're afghans
and so who are these families going to
side with they're going to side with
their sons and their nephews and
brothers are they going to side with an
American occupation Force
we never had any possibility of winning
that war never
amazing John thank you so much now I
allow you your final words and thank you
from the bottom of my heart for being
here with us today thank you Sarah great
to see you my pleasure speaking
bye bye thank you bye thanks